Guide to the Lester Blackwell Granger Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Lester Blackwell Granger papers
1936-1970
JWJ MSS 58
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.08
(5 boxes) + 1 framed art work
The collection consists of writings, notes, clippings, correspondence, and other papers, stemming from Lester Blackwell Granger's work as executive secretary of the National Urban League and his involvement in social work and civil rights issues. Writings consist of annotated and corrected typescript drafts and printed copies of speeches and addresses, autobiographical works, and social commentaries by Granger, as well as some fiction. Also found are papers relating to the National Urban League, a transcript of an interview with Granger, and an oil painting of Granger by Manet Harrison Fowler.
Granger, Lester B. (Lester Blackwell), 1896-1976
Fowler, Manet Harrison, 1895-1976
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from William Reese Co. on the James Weldon Johnson Memorial Collection of Negro Arts & Letters Fund, 2009.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Lester Blackwell Granger (1896-1976)
Lester Blackwell Granger was an African-American civic leader and social worker. Born in 1896, he grew up in Newark, NJ, and graduated from Dartmouth College in 1918. After serving in the United States Army during the First World War, he worked briefly for the Newark chapter of the National Urban League. From 1922 to 1934, Granger was an extension worker with the New Jersey state vocational school for African-American youth in Bordentown. He served on the worker's educational section of the National Urban League from 1934 to 1938, and led the organization's efforts to promote trade unionism among African American workers and challenge racism by employers and labor organizations. He served as assistant executive secretary of the National Urban League from 1940 to 1941 and as executive secretary from 1941 to 1961. He was also a leading figure in social work, serving as president of the National Conference of Social Work in 1952. After retiring from the National Urban League in 1961, Granger joined the faculty of Dillard University in New Orleans, LA, and in 1972 was named Amistad Scholar in Residence there. He died in Alexandria, LA in 1976.
Biographical note is drawn from The African American Registry and the National Association of Social Workers Foundation websites for Granger (accessed on 17 December 2009).
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of writings, notes, clippings, correspondence, and other papers, stemming from Lester Blackwell Granger's work as executive secretary of the National Urban League and his involvement in social work and civil rights issues. Writings consist of annotated and corrected typescript drafts and printed copies of speeches and addresses, autobiographical works, and social commentaries by Granger, as well as some fiction. Also found are papers relating to the National Urban League, a transcript of an interview with Granger, and an oil painting of Granger by Manet Harrison Fowler.
Arrangement
The collection is organized into three series: I. Writings, 1937-1970. II. Other Papers, 1936-1969. III. Art Work, undated.
African American civic leaders; African American social workers; Civic leaders -- United States; Civil Rights movements -- United States -- 20th Century; Social workers -- United States; Oil paintings (visual works); Fowler, Manet Harrison, 1895-1976; Granger, Lester B. (Lester Blackwell), 1896-1976; National Urban League
- Writings, 1937-1970; Series I
  Arrangement
  Largely arranged in alphabetical order by title.
  - Abstract of remarks by Lester B. Granger to be delivered at the opening session of the Michigan Welfare Conference, 1950 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - American Community: A Dynamic Process, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 2-4)
  - American Teamwork - Today and in the Years Ahead (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Annual Report of the Executive Director, National Urban League, 1952 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Autobiography (Box 1, Folder 7-8)
  - Battle-Ax and Bread, 1945-1956 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Barriers to Negro War Employment (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Beauty and the Wonder and the Power (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Biographical (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
  - Biography (Box 1, Folder 14-18)
  - Challenge of Change, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Children and Youth 1960: Assessing the Impact on Them of Economic, Social, and Cultural Factors (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Community Organization, 1961 (Box 1, Folder 21-23)
  - Community Relations Project, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Community Sources of Courage in Children, address by Granger at annual conference of the Child Study Association, 1954 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Counseling Process in Community Planning (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Family (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Field Specialists of the Community Relations Project (Box 2, Folder 28)
  - For Freedom, It Be Now Found (Box 2, Folder 29)
  - Handbook of Counseling Techniques, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 30-32)
  - Harlem Comes of Age, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 33)
  - Harlem Riot - Before and After, 1948 (Box 2, Folder 34)
  - Immigrant (Box 2, Folder 35)
  - Integrated Housing "Social Work's Challenge and Opportunity", 1955 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - International Conference of Social Work Executive Committee Minutes, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - Introductory Remarks (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - "Ironsides" the Bordentown Vocational School, 1940-1950 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Wartime Steps Toward Postwar Security (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Louis Simon Testimonial Dinner (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Manhattan and Beyond, 1948-1960 (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Measuring Rod for Social Progress (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Mission to a New Nation - Ghana's Independence Celebration, 1957 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - National Council of Jewish Women, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Nature and Role of Community Development, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - New Services and Old Needs, address at luncheon meeting of Federation of Protestant Welfare Agencies, 1965 (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - New Trade Union Movements and the Negro Worker, 1937 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - New York Urban League and the Education of Negro Children in New York City, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Notes (Box 3, Folder 50-51)
  - Notes for Address at International Conference of Social Work, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 52)
  - Peace! (Box 3, Folder 53)
  - President, the Negro, and Defense (Box 3, Folder 54)
  - Racial Factor in Our International Relations (Box 3, Folder 55)
  - Remarks at Lester Granger Tribute, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 56)
  - School Desegregation, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 57)
  - Social Component of International Development, address, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 58)
  - Social Development - The Hidden Component (Box 3, Folder 59)
  - Social Work's Response to Democracy's Challenge, 1952 (Box 3, Folder 60-61)
  - Story Thus Far, address, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 62)
  - Suggested as Outline for Article in the Saturday Evening Post, 1954 (Box 3, Folder 63)
  - Testimony of the National Urban League before House Judiciary Committee, 1958 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  - Vespers Service Address at Dillard University, 1962 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  - Mrs. Smith, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 66)
  - Untitled Essay (Box 3, Folder 67-68)
  - Untitled Manuscript and Typescript (Box 3, Folder 69-70)
  - New Poverty, lecture by Raymond Hilliard, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Fragments (Box 3, Folder 72)
- Other Papers, 1936-1969; Series II
  Not arranged in any particular order.
  - Newspaper Clippings, 1936-1960 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - The Changing Image, 1961 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Gary, Indiana Social Case, 1946-1947 (Box 3, Folder 75-76)
  - Interviews with Lester B. Granger, 1968 (Box 4, Folder 77)
  - National Urban League, 1945-1961 (Box 4, Folder 78)
  - National Urban League Excerpts from Remarks at Lester B. Granger Tribute, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 79)
  - National Urban League Press Releases, 1945-1964 (Box 4, Folder 80)
  - Reports, 1960-1968 (Box 4, Folder 81)
  - Resume (Box 4, Folder 82)
  - Black and White Portrait Photograph, 1969 (Box 4, Folder 83)
  - Printed Material, 1939-1961 (Box 4, Folder 84)
  - Correspondence, 1943-1969 (Box 4, Folder 85-87)
- Art Work, undated; Series III
  - Oil painting of Lester Blackwell Granger by Manet Harrison Fowler, undated (Box art, Folder 88)
  - Metal box originally housing oil painting, undated (Box 5)